Guide to the Memory Project Oral History collection, 2009-2016 | 民间记忆计划口述史 RL.10171
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Shanxi Province | 山西省, 2013
  - Beizhuang Village | 忻州市定襄县受禄乡北庄村, 2013
    - Fan Yangwen | 樊扬文, 2013
      Fan Yangwen (b. 1930) is a resident of Beizhuang Village. In this interview Fan recalls about the Japanese soldiers coming into the village and were not bad to the children. He began to work in the field at the age of 13. The socialst commue started in 1955 at his village but life was difficult.
      樊扬文1930年出生，是山西省衡定襄县受禄乡北庄村村民。在这段口述中，樊老人回忆了日本兵进村对小孩子友好的情况。他13岁开始下地干重活。55年公社开始，日子却不好过。
    - Fan Qingwen | 樊庆文, 2013
      Fan Qingwen (b. 1949) is a resident of Beizhuang Village. In this interview Fan says that both his parents passed when he was little. His gradfather committed suicide in 1959 because he was wronged for stealing food when he was actually borrowing consented by the village carders. At the beginning of Cultural Revolution, Fan went to Beijing to participate in a parade as a red guard, and they were received by Chairman Mao on October 18, 1966. Fan also told a story of peasant woman who cursed Mao to death at a village gathering in 1941. Mao didn't actually punish her because her husband was killed fighting in a communist troop and she had three children to raise by herself. Mao started Nanniwan agricultural development experiment to help local peasants and the troops to be self-sufficient.
      樊庆文1949年出生，是山西省衡定襄县受禄乡北庄村村民。在这段口述中，樊老人回忆自己父母早逝，爷爷是大跃进时因饥饿借粮食被冤枉59年自杀死的。文革开始，老人1966年10月18号在北京参加集会并受到毛主席接见。老人还讲了1941年的一个往事：一个农妇在集会时诅咒毛主席被雷击死，因她的丈夫在边区牺牲，家中无劳力，毛主席没有惩罚那妇人，还号召部队帮助生产。
    - Song Dengbao | 宋灯宝, 2013
      Song Dengbao (b. 1933) is a resident of Beizhuang Village. In this interview Song recalls the difficult life during the Great Leap Forward. It was worst from 1958-60 when he had to work in the field in the day and carry ores to factories at night. Some people starved to death, many had chronic diseases because of the hardship. Things got a little better from 1963. The real improvement came when Deng Xiaoping became in charge.
      宋灯宝1933年出生，是山西省衡定襄县受禄乡北庄村村民。在这段口述中，宋老人回忆了大跃进那时，白天忙农活，晚上赶车运矿石，肚子饿着只能紧紧裤带。58-60年最糟糕，有人饿死，很多人落下病根。63年情况有点好转。邓小平执政后才真正好起来。
    - Song Shuangyin | 宋双印, 2013
      Song Shuangyin (b. 1937) is a resident of Beizhuang Village. In this interview Fan recalls the hardship during the Commue Canteen period. A person was supposed to get one Jin per day, children and elderly were given less, actually people got much less than this and were very hungry. Song went to Beidi and worked on construction for one year becuase he would get more food this way.
      宋双印1937年出生，是山西省衡定襄县受禄乡北庄村村民。在这段口述中，宋老人回忆了吃食堂吃不饱的经历。每人每天一斤，小孩老人分量少些，真正吃到的比这更少。老人因此去北路干活一年，因为那里吃的好些。
    - Fan Lanxiang | 樊兰香, 2013
      Fan Lanxiang (b. 1957) is a resident of Beizhuang Village. In this interview Fan recalls that the commue canteen started in 1958. Food was very limited, and her grandfather died of starvation, and a few other elder villagers also died the same way.
      樊兰香1957年出生，是山西省衡定襄县受禄乡北庄村村民。在这段口述中，樊老人回忆了58年公社食堂开始，食物极少，爷爷饿死了，同村还有几个老人饿死。
- Sichuan province | 四川省, 2013
  - Longju Village | 泸州市合江县白米乡龙聚村, 2013
    Longju Village is located in Hejiang County, Luzhou City, Sichuan Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Wu Wenguang.
    龙聚村位于四川省泸州市合江县白米乡。村民的录像采访人是吴文光。
    - Li Zhezhen | 李泽珍, 2013
    - Cheng Wenbi | 程文碧, 2013
      Cheng Wenbi (b. 1945) is a resident in Longju Village, Baimi Town, Hejiang County, Sichuan Province. Her family moved here from another village as poor peasants during the Land Reform. In this interview, Cheng remembers the communal dining hall during the Great Famine, all kinds of food people ate at that time, and her family members (mother, younger sister, grandmother, two uncles) who starved to death.
      程文碧1945年出生，是四川省合江市白米乡龙聚村的村民。土改时她和家人作为贫雇农从另一个村子搬了过来。 在这段口述中，程老人回忆了伙食团时期的集体食堂，那时人们吃的各种食物，还有她饿死的家人（母亲，妹妹，外婆，两个叔叔）。
    - Li Chenyu | 李成玉, 2013
      Li Chengyu (b. 1946) was born in Yuhewan Village, Juewu Town, Hejiang County, Sichuan Province，and now lives in Longju Village, Baimi Town. In this interview, Li remembers her bitter life since she was four years old. When China was just 'liberated' in 1949, the Li family was classified as 'landlord'; everything was confiscated and her mother was taken for struggle sessions. In 1958, People's Communes were established, not only communal canteen was established in place of family ones, neighbors were forced to live together. Without enough food, she ate whatever she could find. Due to the landlord class, her mother's family was given very little food and five people starved to death.
      李成玉1946年出生于四川泸州市合江县觉悟乡玉河湾村，现居白米乡龙聚村。在这段口述中，李老人回忆了她从4岁开始的苦日子。1949年刚'解放'时，李成玉家被判为'地主成份'，东西统统没收，妈妈被抓去批斗。1958年公社化开始后，不仅食堂实行集体化，邻里也强迫搬到一起住。因为食物不够，她什么都找来吃过。因为地主成份，她妈妈家分到的粮食少，饿死了五个人。
    - Xian Zhongshi | 先宗诗, 2013
      Xian Zongshi (b. 1944) lives in Longju Village, Baimi Town Hejiang County, Sichuan Province. He is the other interviewee, Cheng Wenbi's husband; they moved together to the Wu family's house after land reform. In this interview, Xian recalls his experiences during the Great Famine. Because his father died in the early fifties, his mother with bounded feet had to earn work points with the children when People's Commune was established in 1958. Xian ate whatever available at the time, and got terribly ill. In 1961, the Production Team cadres and the keeper divided the village's grains among themselves and accused the Liu brothers (Liu Chaoyun, Liu Chaogui, who are also interviewed) of stealing. They also took away the animals raised by the villagers to make up for the grains. Xian became the Production Team leader between 1972 and 1983, and has taken revenge on these old cadres during the Cultural Revolution.
      先宗诗1944年出生，现居四川省泸州市合江县白米乡龙聚村。他是另一位被访人程文碧的丈夫，土改时作为贫农一起搬到吴家。在这段口述中，先老人回忆了他在大饥荒期间的经历。他的父亲50年代初就去世了，人民公社开始后，只有裹脚的母亲带着孩子抢工分。当时正在长身体的先宗诗什么都吃过，还得了'湿黄病'。生产队的干部和保管员1961年私分了公粮，却诬陷说是刘家的兄弟偷了，还拖走村民的牲口来抵粮。先宗诗1972年到1983年是队长，在文革时也对这些老干部实施了报复。
    - Wu Tinyi | 吴廷易, 2013
      Wu Tinyi (b. 1937) was born in Longju Village, Baimi Town, Hejiang County, Sichuan Province. As a son from a landlord's family, Wu's life has been strongly influenced by his class background. In this interview, he recollects about the struggles of poor peasants against landlords. He also recalls his experience during the Great Leap Forward after the village started the People's Commune in 1957. He talks about all kinds of food people ate during the Great Famine, and the struggle against village cadres during the Cultural Revolution.
      吴廷易1937年出生于四川省合江市白米乡龙聚村。他的一生被地主子女的阶级背景深深影响。 在这段口述中，吴老人回忆了土改时贫下中农斗地主，大跃进时他（1957年）加入人民公社后的所见所闻，大饥荒期间人们吃的各种东西，还有文革时对村里干部的批斗。
    - Wu Tinqia | 吴廷恰, 2013
      Wu Tinqia (b. 1942) was born in Longju Village, Baimi Town, Hejiang County, Sichuan Province. In this interview, he talks about his family being classified as landlord, two were even killed during the Land Reform. He talks about what people ate and how some stole food during the Great Famine. He also remembers the struggle sessions during the Cultural Revolution.
      吴廷恰1942年出生于四川省合江市白米乡龙聚村。在这段口述中，他说起了土改时吴家被判为地主，有两人被枪毙。大饥荒时期人们吃的东西，有人偷食物，还有文革时的批斗会。
  - Xiangyang Village | 泸州市合江县白米乡向阳村, 2013
    Xiangyang Village is located in Hejiang County, Luzhou City, Sichuan Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Wu Wenguang.
    向阳村位于四川省泸州市合江县白米乡。村民的录像采访人是吴文光。
    - Liu Yuqing | 刘玉清 (刘清云？）, 2013
    - Liu Chaogui | 刘朝贵, 2013
      Liu Chaogui (b. 1937) is a resident of Longju Village, Baimi Town Hejiang County, Sichuan Province. He is Liu Chaoyun's younger brother. In this interview, Liu recalls his experiences during the Great Famine, such as being in charge of the food tickets at People's Commune canteen, working at the Production Team, and being falsely accused of stealing. He thinks people starved 'not (because) the country persecuted the people, but the people persecuted the country, the people persecuted the people'.
      刘朝贵1937年出生，是四川省泸州市合江县白米乡龙聚村的村民。他是刘朝云的弟弟。在这段口述中，刘老人回忆了大饥荒期间的经历，包括吃食堂时管饭票，搞生产和被诬陷偷粮食。他认为人们挨饿'不是（因为）国家整人民，是人民整国家, 人民整人民'。
    - Chen Shuxian | 陈淑仙, 2013
      Chen Shuxian (b. 1928) lives in Xiangyang Village, Baimi Town Hejiang County, Sichuan Province. She is from a 'poor peasant' family, and was the director of the village committee of the Women's Federation during the land reform. In this interview, Chen recalls the experience of starvation during the Great Famine. She also talks about the reason for the famine: Mao Zedong called for production increase but the cadres exaggerated the production too much.
      陈淑仙1928年出生,现居四川省泸州市合江县白米乡向阳村。她出身贫农，土改时是妇女主任。在这段口述中，陈老人回忆了大饥荒期间挨饿的经历。她还说饥荒的原因是毛泽东号召增产以及干部虚报产量。
    - Luo Zhaoying | 罗招英, 2013
      Luo Zhaoying (b.1933) lives in Longju Village, Baimi Town Hejiang County, Sichuan Province. In this interview, Luo recalls her experiences during the Great Famine. When eating at the People's Commune canteen, she has eaten anything, even raw grasshoppers. Her father-in-law starved to death due to edema disease.
      罗招英1933年出生，现居四川省泸州市合江县白米乡龙聚村。在这段口述中，罗老人回忆了大饥荒期间的经历。她在吃食堂的时候，什么都找来吃，甚至生吃过蚂蚱。她的公公饿出了水肿病，死了。
    - Hu Naiqing | 胡乃清, 2013
      Hu Naiqing (b. 1938) lives in Xiangyang Village, Baimi Town Hejiang County, Sichuan Province. In this interview, Hu recalls the experience at People's Commune canteen during the Great Famine, and what people ate when they were starved.
      胡乃清1938年出生，现居四川省泸州市合江县白米乡向阳村。在这段口述中，胡老人回忆了大饥荒期间吃食堂的经历，以及最饿的时候找来吃的东西。
    - Liu Chaoyun | 刘朝云, 2013
      Liu Chaoyun (b. 1933) is a resident of Longju Village, Baimi Town Hejiang County, Sichuan Province. He is Liu Chaogui's older brother. In this interview, Liu talks about his experience during the Great Famine. Whether constructing blast furnace or working for the Production Team during the Great Leap forward, some people worked hard, some didn't. Honest people had a rougher time. His father got edema disease and starved to death in 1959 when eating at the People's Commune canteen. The situation did not improve until households were allowed to contract land from the collective.
      刘朝云1933年出生，是四川省泸州市合江县白米乡龙聚村的村民。他是刘朝贵的大哥。在这段口述中，刘老人讲述了大饥荒期间的经历。在大跃进炼钢铁时或是生产队上工作时，都有人干活有人偷懒，老实的人就吃苦。他的父亲1959年吃食堂的时候得水肿病饿死了。直到田土被下放人们才又不挨饿了。
  - Banli Village | 泸州市合江县白米乡板栗村, 2013
    Banli Village is located in Hejiang County, Luzhou City, Sichuan Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Wu Wenguang.
    板栗村位于四川省泸州市合江县白米乡。村民的录像采访人是吴文光。
    - Liu Dunping | 刘敦平, 2013
      Liu Dunping (b.1946) was born in Banli Village, Baimi Town, Hejiang County, Sichuan Province. In this interview, Liu talks about life during the Great Famine. Although his family had neither land nor house, they were classified as 'rich peasant' because of conflict with the chairman of the peasant association. They got less food in the People's Commune canteen and earned fewer work points. After his father starved to death in 1961, 14-year-old Liu Dunping quit school and worked at home, taking care of three younger sisters and his mother.
      刘敦平1946年出生于四川泸州市合江县白米乡板栗村。在这段口述中，刘老人讲述了大饥荒时期的生活。家中虽然没地没房产，却因为得罪农会主席被定为'富农成份'。在食堂分到的食物少，干活挣的工分也少。1961年父亲饿死后，14岁的刘敦平退学回家劳动，照顾三个妹妹和母亲。
    - Mu Liangzhao | 穆良昭, 2013
      Mu Liangzhao (b.1950) was born in Chenwuji Village, Baiguo Town, Hejiang County, Sichuan Province, and now lives in Banli Village, Baimi Town, Hejiang County. In this interview, Mu recalls life during the Great Famine. In 1958, Mu Liangzhao quit school when she was at third grade and stayed at home to work. She clearly remembers what she had eaten when there was not enough food at the People's Commune canteen, as well as the experience of stealing food from Production Team's field. In 1960, her father, sister-in-law and two nieces all starved to death.
      穆良昭1950年出生于四川省泸州市合江县白果乡陈屋基村，现居合江县白米乡板栗村。在这段口述中，穆老人回忆了大饥荒期间的生活。1958年，小学三年级的穆良昭退学回家干活。她清楚地记得食堂不够吃的时候找来吃的东西以及去生产队地里偷吃的经历。1960年，她的父亲，嫂子和两个侄女都饿死了。
- Yunnan province | 云南省, 2010-2016
  - Gaojia Village | 昆明市富民县款庄乡高家村, 2010
    Gaojia Village is located in Fumin County, Kunming City, Yunnan Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Wu Wenguang.
    高家村位于云南省昆明市富民县款庄乡。村民的录像采访人是吴文光。
    - Gu Ming | 顾明, 2010
      Gu Ming (b. 1943) was born in Gaojia Village, Fumin County, Kunmin City, Yunnan Province. In this interview, Gu recalls his experiences during the Great Famine. In 1958, he worked at the reservoir, and once worked continuously for ten days and night. People ate very well when People's Commune canteen first began, but that did not last long. Because his brother was the head of the canteen, Gu did not starve as much as others did. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      顾明1943年出生于云南省昆明市富民县款庄乡蒣谷高家村。在这段口述中，顾老人回忆了大饥荒时期的经历。1958年，顾明上水库工地干活，有一次持续工作了十天十夜。伙食团刚开始时吃的很好，但过了一段时间粮食就不够了。因为哥哥是伙食团的'老总'，他才比别人饿得少一些。
    - Li Meiying | 李美英, 2010
    - Ni Meilan | 倪美兰, 2010
      Ni Meilan (b. 1942) lives in Gaojia Village, Fumin County, Kunmin City, Yunnan Province. In this interview, Ni talks about her experiences from 1958 to 1961 (during the Great Famine). She joined the Great Leap Forward and Great Collaboration at 16 years old. Without enough cattle for plowing, people did it themselves, and someone died because of that. Once Ni got caught stealing food; not only were her work points deducted, she was forbidden to eat for three days. In May 1959, her parents were poisoned to death because they were too old to work. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      倪美兰1942年出生，1959年嫁到了云南省昆明市富民县款庄乡蒣谷高家村。在这段口述中，倪老人讲述了她从1958年到1961年（大饥荒）的经历。她16岁参加大跃进，去搞大协作。当时犁地牛不够，让人去，有人活活拉犁拉死了。有一次她偷吃东西被发现，不仅工分被扣，还被罚三天不许吃饭。1959年5月，她的父母因为不是劳动力被人毒死了。
    - Li Xingfu | 李兴富, 2010
      Li Xingfu (b.1933) was born in Gaojia Village, Fumin County, Kunmin City, Yunnan Province (where the interviewer used to be an intellectual youth). In this interview, Li recalls his experience at the People's Commune canteen during the Great Famine. He clearly remembers how much grain each person got at that time and the starvation he experienced.
      李兴富1933年出生于云南省昆明市富民县款庄乡蒣谷高家村 （采访人曾经在此插队）。在这段口述中，李老人回忆了大饥荒期间吃食堂的经历。他还清楚地记得当时分得多少粮食以及一些挨饿的轶事。
    - Sun Shaomei | 孙绍美, 2010
      Sun Shaomei (b.1932) is a resident in Yuxueshan Village, Fumin County, Kunmin City, Yunnan Province. In this interview, Sun recalls the bitter days during the Great Famine. During the day, while carrying her child, she cut firewood, carried water and cooked for the People's Commune canteen. At night, she also made straw sandals.
      孙绍美1932年出生,是云南省昆明市富民县款庄乡蒣谷小白坡村的村民。在这段口述中，孙老人回忆了大饥荒期间的苦日子。她白天带着孩子去砍柴挑水，給食堂做饭，晚上还要打草鞋。
  - Jiaochangba Village | 昆明市富民县款庄镇校场坝村, 2016
    Jiaochangba Village is located in Fumin County, Kunming City, Yunnan Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Wu Wenguang.
    校场坝村位于云南省昆明市富民县款庄乡。村民的录像采访人是吴文光。
    - Li Jiade | 李家德, 2016
      Li Jiade (b.1940) is a resident of Jiaochangba Village, Kuanzhuang, Fuming County, Kunming, Yunnan Province. He is the older brother of Li Jiaren. He was born in a poor peasant family and never went to school. He was a production team leader for over two decades. During the Great Leap Forward, they worked every day, which was called 'launching satellites'. Their goal was to surpass the iron and steel output in the US and the UK. During farming seasons, they could have six liang of grains per day; at other times, only five liang. They were constantly starved. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      李家德（1937年出生）是云南省昆明市富民县款庄乡校场坝村村民，李家仁的哥哥。他出生贫农，没念过书，当了二十多年的生产队长。大跃进期间，他们每天干活，被称为'放卫星'，目标是使中国的钢铁量赶超英美。他们农忙的时候可以吃六两粮食，平时五两，饥饿难耐。
    - Li Jiaren | 李家仁, 2016
      Li Jiaren (b.1940) is a resident of Jiaochangba Village, Kuanzhuang, Fuming County, Kunming, Yunnan Province. He is the younger brother of Li Jiade. During the Great Leap Forward, Li Jiaren was a teenager in school. There was no food at home, so he and his family could only wait for canteen meals every day. There were grains stored in the village barns but only cadres dared to steal from there. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      李家仁（1940年生）是云南省昆明市富民县款庄乡校场坝村村民，李家德的弟弟。大跃进期间，李家仁十几岁，还在学校念书，家里没有东西吃，每天等食堂开饭。仓库里有粮食，但只有干部敢偷吃。
    - Xiong Jiahong | 熊家红, 2016
      Xiong Jiahong (b. 1937) is a resident of Jiaochangba Village, Kuanzhuang, Fuming County, Kunming, Yunnan Province. Xiong was born in a poor peasant family and was a production team leader for a few years. During the Great Leap Forward, Xiong worked every day with his fellow villagers but they didn't have enough to eat. He complained about to some cadres but was accused of being 'reactionary' by cadres. Xiong's wife Yang Shizhen came from a landlord family in a nearby village. Xiong was too poor to afford betrothal gifts, so he married this landlord's daughter who didn't ask for any betrothal gifts. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      熊家红（1937年生）是云南省昆明市富民县款庄乡校场坝村村民。熊家红出身贫农，当过四五年生产队长。大跃进期间，熊老人和其他人天天劳动，却填不饱肚子，和干部抱怨，被指反动。熊老人的妻子杨世珍来自邻村一个地主家庭。熊老人因为家里没有钱买彩礼，所以娶了不需要彩礼的地主家女儿。
    - Li Xingke | 李兴科, 2016
      Li Xingke (b.1934) is a resident of Jiaochangba Village, Kuanzhuang, Fuming County, Kunming, Yunnan Province. Li Xingke was born in a poor peasant family and never went to school. He was a production team leader for over a decade. During the period of communal canteens, villagers were drafted to work outside their village and few people were left to work in the field. There was little production as result of this. Li said that Chairman Mao was always right. Nobody died of hunger there, but some got sick because of hunger and died eventually. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      李兴科（1934年生）是云南省昆明市富民县款庄乡校场坝村村民。李兴科出身贫农，没上过学，当过十几年的生产队队长。吃集体食堂时期，劳动力被外调，无人生产粮食，所以没有很多东西吃。李老人说毛主席做的事情都是对的。当地没有人饿死，但是有人饿出病来，随后去世。
    - Yang Shizhen | 杨世珍, 2016
      Yang Shizhen (b.1939) is a resident of Jiaochangba Village, Kuanzhuang, Fuming County, Kunming, Yunnan Province. Yang is Xiong Jiahong's wife and she cannot manage her daily life on her own. During the Land Reform, Yang's family was classified as landlord. Out of fear, her father hanged himself. Her mother was locked up for a month. Since her mother was sick, 12-year-old Yang Shizhen went to struggle session in lieu of her parents. She got married at the age of 18 and then had 10 children, 5 of which died at the age of 2 or 3. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      杨世珍（1939年生）是云南省昆明市富民县款庄乡校场坝村村民。杨世珍是熊家红的妻子，生活不能自理。土地改革期间，她家被评为地主后，其父由于恐惧，上吊自杀，其母被关押一个月。由于母亲患病，十二岁的杨世珍代父母去参加批斗大会。她十八岁嫁人，生了十个孩子，五个在两三岁的时候病死。
    - Li Meicui | 李美翠, 2016
      Li Meicui (b. 1939) is a resident of Jiaochangba Village, Kuanzhuang, Fuming County, Kunming, Yunnan Province. She is the wife of Li Jiade. Li moved to her current village after getting married when she was 18. She gave birth to three children. During the Great Leap Forward, she brought her two little kids to work every day and did all kinds of work. Her kids cried when they were hungry but she had nothing to feed them. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      李美翠（1939年生）是云南省昆明市富民县款庄乡校场坝村村民，是另一位被采访人李家德的妻子。李老人十八岁的时候从外地嫁过来，生了三个孩子。大跃进期间，她每天带着自己两个年幼的孩子出工，做各种各样的工作。孩子饿了会边哭边叫，但是她没有东西喂孩子吃。
  - Xiaobaipo Village | 昆明市富民县款庄乡小白坡村, 2010-2016
    Xiaobaipo Village is located in Fumin County, Kunming City, Yunnan Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Wu Wenguang.
    小白坡村位于云南省昆明市富民县款庄乡。村民的录像采访人是吴文光。
    - Pan Zhongmei | 潘宗美, 2010
      Pan Zhongmei (b. 1941) was born in Xiaobaipo Village, Fumin County, Kunmin City, Yunnan Province. She was the accountant in the village during the Great Famine. In this interview, Pan recalls her experiences at that time. When People's Commune canteen started, she calculated work points to decide how much food each person could get. Some cadres stole grains home, but she 'did not dare to speak up, did not dare to interfere'. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      潘宗美1941年出生于云南省昆明市富民县款庄乡蒣谷小白坡村。她在大饥荒期间是村里的会计。在这段口述中，潘老人回忆了当时的经历。伙食团开始后，她每天要统计工分来算給多少吃的。当干部的会把粮食偷回家，但她'不敢说，不敢管'。
    - Li Guoen | 李国恩, 2016
      Li Guoen (b.1935) is a resident of Xiaobaipo Village, Kuanzhuang, Fuming County, Kunming, Yunnan Province. He was born in a landlord family, which was once the richest family in the village. They had the largest yard in the village. During the Land Reform, the yard was used as the brigade's office, medical station and village store. Li Guoen was fairly young when his family properties were confisticated and redistributed. Since he had finished elementary school, he was sent to be an account in another village. He tried his best not to exaggerate harvest amount in the village so their team wasn't gravely starved. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      李国恩（1935年生）是云南省昆明市富民县款庄乡小白坡村村民。他出生于地主家庭，他家曾是该村首富，有全村最大的院子。土地改革期间，这个院子充公作为大队办公室，医疗站，卖东西的商店。 那时李国恩年龄还小，家庭财产被重新分配。他因为读过小学，被抽调去另外一个村做会计。他尽量不虚报粮食产量，所以他们队没有挨很多饿
    - Xiong Yun | 熊云, 2016
      Xiong Yun (b. 1940) is a resident of Xiaobaipo Village, Kuanzhuang, Fuming County, Kunming, Yunnan Province. During the period of communal canteens, Xiong was a teenager. Many people were slowly starved to death. Thus, a 'nutrition canteen' was set up to amass sick people and serve a little bit more rice. Later when individual families could keep pigs, people had to hand in their pork and offer a pig tail as evidence. Xiong was a teacher in a non-public school in the village and was paid poorly. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      熊云（1940年生）是云南省昆明市富民县款庄乡小白坡村村民。公社食堂时期，熊老人才十几岁。当时很多人慢慢饿死，于是当地办了'营养食堂'，把身体差的人聚集起来多给他们一点米。每家可以养猪以后，杀猪必须上交，并拿猪尾巴证明。他在村里当民办教师，待遇很差。
  - Xugu Village | 昆明市富民县款庄镇蒣谷村, 2016
    Xugu Village is located in Fumin County, Kunming City, Yunnan Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Wu Wenguang.
    徐（蒣）谷村位于云南省昆明市富民县款庄乡。村民的录像采访人是吴文光。
    - Li Fuxuan | 李富选, 2016
      Li Fuxuan (b. 1935) is a resident of Xugu Village, Kuanzhuang, Fuming County, Kunming, Yunnan Province. Li attended school till third grade and then started to work as an apprentice with his father to learn to flatten out felts. His family was classified as poor peasant and got two acres of land. Li participated in some struggle sessions. Peasants were encouraged to vent out their grievances and beat up the denounced. During the Great Leap Forward, villagers worked every day but they didn't work hard. They could finish the work in a village overnight so the crops were not taken proper care of at all. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      李富选（1932年生）是云南省昆明市富民县款庄乡蒣谷村村民。李老人回忆，他读书读到小学三年级以后，便跟着父亲学手艺，擀羊毛。他们家被评为贫农，分得了两亩地。李老人参与了批斗，农民被启发诉苦，然后打被批斗的人。大跃进期间，农民天天干活却都是马虎了事，一夜完成一个村子，庄稼都被搞烂了。
    - Dong Cuimei | 董翠美, 2016
      Dong Cuimei (b. 1942) is a resident of Xugu Village, Kuanzhuang, Fuming County, Kunming, Yunnan Province. During the period of communal canteens, she was 12 years old and didn't starve. She recollects people wearing coarse clothing, self-made shoes and living in thatched cottages. During the Cultural Revolution, because their village was relatively remote, life wasn't much affected there. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      董翠美（1942年生）是云南省昆明市富民县款庄乡蒣谷村村民。公社食堂期间，她十二岁，没有挨饿。她回忆了当时人们穿粗布衣，自己缝制鞋子，住茅草房。文革期间，他们村由于比较偏远，没有受到太大影响。
    - Zhou Zhengying | 周正英, 2010
    - Jiao Meilan | 角美兰, 2010
    - Hu Xiuying | 胡秀英, 2010
  - Yuxueshan Village | 昆明市富民县款庄乡蒣谷玉学山村, 2010
    Yuxueshan Village is located in Fumin County, Kunming City, Yunnan Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Wu Wenguang.
    玉学山村位于\云南省昆明市富民县款庄乡。村民的录像采访人是吴文光。